A Guide to the James Rogers McConnell Memorial Collections
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Printed and Miscellaneous
  - Article, "With the American Ambulance," The Outlook, by James Rogers McConnell. Inscribed "To old pal Paul/J. R. McConnell." Complete issue of The Outlook present., 1915 Sep 15 (Box Box 2)
  - Biographical Sketch of James Rogers McConnell, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Memoir by Mme. Marcelle Guérin de Précourt, with a photograph of the Guérin de Précourt family. Accompanying letter from Paul Ayres Rockwell relates to the memoir and World War I history., 1976 (Box Box 2)
  - Newspaper Articles re James Rogers McConnell, 1914-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - Pamphlet, "Lafayette Escadrille Memorial/To the Pilots of the Lafayette Escadrille and Lafayette Flying Corps," with a subscription form, [1928] (Box Box 2)
  - Pamphlet, "War Letters of Kiffin Yates Rockwell (Supplement)", post 1945 (Box Box 2)
  - Poem, "Mac," by Emory Pottle, post 1917 Mar 19 (Box Box 2)
  - Poem, untitled, by James Rogers McConnell to Alice Graves, ca. 1914 Dec (Box Box 2)
  - Program, "Théâtre du Parc/Dépot des Éclopés de Vitry-le-François/Concert," bearing autograph comment by James Rogers McConnell, 1916 Sep 17 (Box Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Ambulance driver James Rogers McConnell and Foreign Legionnaire Paul Ayres Rockwell, [1915] (Box Box 2)
  - First four pilots to report to the Lafayette Escadrille and their commanding officer. Taken at Luxeuil, Vosges, 1916 Apr 20 (Box Box 2)
    Pictured: James Rogers McConnell, Kiffin Yates Rockwell, Norman Prince, Captain Georges Thenault, and Victor Chapman.
  - James Rogers McConnell, Victor Chapman, and Kiffin Yates Rockwell shooting pool at Madames Voge's Billiard Parlor, the Pomme d'Or, 1916 Apr (Box Box 2)
  - Original "Escadrille Americaine" at Luxeuil-les-Bains, France, 1916 Apr (Box Box 2)
    Pictured: from left, Victor Chapman (1st), Captain Georges Thenault (5th), Norman Prince (7th), Kiffin Yates Rockwell (8th), James Rogers McConnell (last), and "Whiskey" in front.
  - First briefing of the Lafayette Escadrille, 1916 ca. Apr (Box Box 2)
    Pictured: Kiffin Yates Rockwell, Captain Georges Thenault, Norman Prince, Lieutenant de Laage de Meux, Elliot [Christopher] Cowdin, Bert Hall, James Rogers McConnell, and Victor Chapman.
  - James Rogers McConnell and his two French mechanics beside his plane bearing the University of Virginia Hot Foot Society emblem, 1916 Jul (Box Box 2)
  - James Rogers McConnell, in the uniform of the French Air Force, standing before his plane, 1916 Jul (Box Box 2)
  - James Rogers McConnell, in the uniform of the French Air Force, standing by his plane bearing the University of Virginia Hot Foot emblem, 1916 Jul (Box Box 2)
  - Kiffin Yates Rockwell and James Rogers McConnell, [ante 1916 Sep 23] (Box Box 2)
  - James Rogers McConnell and Paul Ayres Rockwell on Rockwell's wedding day. [Notes by William James Kenneth Rockwell concerning this photograph and its history], 1916 Dec 4 (Box Box 2)
  - Allied Air Forces Party at Cachy, France, [1916-1917 Winter] (Box Box 2)
    Pictured: James Rogers McConnell, Willis Bradley Haviland, Dudley Lawrence Hill, Paul Pavelka, Lieutenant de Laage de Meux, Robert Lockerbie Rockwell, and three unidentified pilots
  - Lafayette Escadrille at Chaudun, France, 1917 (Box Box 2)
    Pictured: Front row, left to right: Didier Masson, Stephen Sohier Bigelow, Charles Chouteau Johnson, William Thaw, Captain Georges Thénault, Edwin Charles Parsons, Thomas Moses Hewitt, Harold Buckley Willis, and Willis Haviland. Back row, left to right: Ray Claflin Bridgman, Robert Lockerbie Rockwell, Henry Sweet Jones, David Peterson, William Edward Dugan, Douglas MacMonagle, Walter Lovell, and Lieutenant Arnoux de Maison-Rouge
  - First grave of James Rogers McConnell at Petit-Detroit, near Flavey-le-Martel, (Aisne), France, 1918 Mar (Box Box 2)
    Pictured: Paul Ayres Rockwell and Wilbur Forest.
  - Grave of James Rogers McConnell, near Flavey-le-Martel, France, ca. 1918 (Box Box 2)
  - Portrait of James Rogers McConnell in business suit [printed in a magazine following his death], n.d. (Box Box 2)
- Audiovisual
  - Lafayette Escadrille. Film (16 mm.) of the original Escadrille Américaine at Luxeuil-les- Bains., 1916; Films: F-155
- Other
  - Gold cigarette case given to James Rogers McConnell by Paul Ayres Rockwell on the day of Rockwell's wedding to Mlle. Jeanne Leyges. Engraved "J. R. McC. en Souvenir du 4 December 1916.", 1916 Dec 4 (Box Mini Tray 5)
  - French broadside from the people of Luxeuil, France in commemoration of wartime Franco-American relations. Noted are General Stanley H. Ford, Paul Rockwell, Captain Nazare- Aga, Maurice de Barneville, Madam Ovington, and the Le Comité D'Organisation, [1931] (Box Oversize Tray 32)
  - McConnell family: Crenshaw, great-grandmother; Samuel Parsons McConnell, father, with James McConnell Truitt; Sarah Rogers McConnell, mother, at ages 25 and 60-65; Julia McConnell, sister, at age 47, ca. 1880-1930 (Box Prints File)
  - Monument dedicated to James Rogers McConnell, located in Carthage, North Carolina. Two photos taken by Chuck Bigger., 1977 (Box Prints File)